# Ramakrishna Nalla

+1 (424) 625 5275

ramakrishna.nalla@gmail.com

# FULL STACK ENGINEER

Engineering Manager • Technical Lead • Specialized in Designing Web Applications

Comprehensive background in modern industry-adopted JS technologies for large-scale enterprise initiatives.

Full Stack Architect and Engineer with decades of comprehensive experience in modern Front-end frameworks and developing rich user experience for critical enterprise applications. Developed a customer service chatbot using the OpenAI API to automate 80% of common inquiries. Solid understanding of view layout and rendering technologies. Extensive experience in web-based applications and high-level proficiency in JavaScript, React, Angular, Node, HTML, and CSS technologies. Demonstrated strengths in building APIs using Node, REST, and GraphQL APIs. Experienced with Web Application Architecture for optimized performance. Designed and architected 2000+ React and Angular components. Experience working with a large team of developers, QA Engineers, and scrum masters. Experience in building CI/CD pipelines using Jenkins, Docker, and custom scripts. Proven ability to effectively plan, coordinate, and meet deadlines, and business expectations for medium to large-scale projects.

# TECHNICAL PROFICIENCIES

Angular • React-Redux-Hooks • Node JS • RxJS • Single SPA MFE • ExpressJS • Jest• Jasmine • Karma • Open AI • AWS GraphQL • RESTful API • Apigee • HTML • CSS Frameworks • SASS • Style • Build Tools • Babel • TypeScript • WebPack CICD • Docker • Git • MongoDB • Agile Scrum • SAFe • Jira • Rally • Adobe Photoshop • Invision• Figma

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Marsh Insurance, Phoenix, AZ

2020 - Present

## Lead Software Engineer and Architect - LINQ Application (2020 - Present)

Technical Lead, Senior Software Engineer for an Enterprise Web Application of 3000+ clients. Charged with providing hands-on across all full-stack initiatives in application development with performance. Led all project functions, including requirements analysis, development, sprint planning, and stakeholder communication. Ensure successful project/feature completion within an Agile environment.

- Designed, architected, and collaborated in developing application with 200+ reusable components, to increase developer efficiency by 30%.
- Led the design and development of 50+ RESTful Node.js APIs using MongoDB along with OpenAI API.
- Implemented JWT token-based authentication and Apigee API management to ensure API security and scalability.
- Designed a micro frontend and microservices architecture, increasing release cycles by 30%.
- Led initiatives to reduce code duplication by 20% by implementing the Factory pattern to create components, improving maintainability, performance and reducing development time for new features.
- Developed OKTA SSO using OAuth 2.0 OIDC and integrated it with Marsh-connected Apps.
- Led MFE development for React, Angular. Implemented 20+ GUI dashboards using amChats and D3 js.
- Developed and implemented a component-based architecture for a complex web application, resulting in a 30% reduction in development time for new features, with improved web security and accessibility standards.
- Collaborated with DevOps engineers to implement continuous integration and continuous delivery (CI/CD) pipelines for micro front-ends, enabling faster and more reliable deployments.
- Demonstrated strong leadership and collaboration skills in resolving critical application issues, by working with across geographically dispersed development and support teams, such as Google for analytics and map integration.
- Integrated security analysis tools (DataDog, Sonar, WhiteHat, Sysdig, Git Guardians) and empowered the team to fix and prevent vulnerabilities.
- Championed 30+ initiatives to improve code quality, reviews, versioning, and the deployment process, fostering a culture of continuous improvement.
- Collaborated with external technical teams to develop feature-managed web applications, which resulted in smooth, on-demand feature releases.
- Led initiatives to improve web security and accessibility, and mentored the team in resolving 250+ critical bugs, significantly enhancing application stability and performance.

## American Express Technologies, Phoenix, AZ

2010 - 2019

Senior Web Developer -Instant Card Number (2016 - 2019)

An integral member of the Enterprise Web Application charged with providing hands-on across all front-end initiatives in application development, performance, RWD, accessibility, and redesigns using React and Angular tech-stacks.

- Led the front-end development and collaboratively worked with **Google** and **Samsung** teams for Digital wallet
- Architected and developed ICN application using Angular JS with 8,00+ reusable components
- Built a fully scalable SPA (Single Page Application) application for more than 50k user traffic. The application generated more than \$2M worth of revenue for American Express.
- Implemented RUM scripts, Splunk dashboard, and API performance metrics using in-house tools.
- Created CI/CD pipeline using Jenkins and custom scripts; WebPack build and GIT workflow optimizations.
- Successfully partnered with the geographically dispersed support teams to resolve highly critical front-end issues.
- Collaborated with external agencies like Digitas, and Space 150 to develop high-performing web applications for American Express which resulted in a growth of 5% incremental card acquisitions

## AMERICAN EXPRESS, Phoenix, AZ/New York, NY

# Technical LEAD/Front-end Developer - US Digital Acquisition, Card Shop & Card App (2015 - 2016)

Charged with the role of a Technical Lead for end-to-end front-end development. Bridged the gap between back-end engineering and offshore departments by leading/participating in daily stand-ups, driving change management, and leveraging technical acumen through all project phases.

# Technical LEAD/Front-end Developer - US Digital Acquisition, CCSG, OPEN, and API (2010 - 2015)

- Developed a web application and supported a \$5M annual digital marketing program.
- Led the development and launch of a \$1.2M mobile site, managing an offshore team and collaborating with cross-functional engineering teams.
- Improved performance scores by 50% better scores for Google page-speed, yslow, and XpressScan.
- Resolved 250+ critical bugs to enhance application performance and user experience.
- Developed and deployed system enhancements for partner integration with **Amazon Prime**, utilizing new technologies to integrate the application within the partner's infrastructure.

## **Additional Experience:**

# AMERICAN EXPRESS - Junior Web Developer - US Digital Acquisition CCSG

2007 - 2010

Successfully contributed to the complete redesign of the UI of the application. Developed a componentized UI framework using JQuery, AJAX, Zepto, Moo tools, and DOJO frameworks

- Delivered a solid, bug-free high-performance code with active collaboration with QA Engineers
- Mentored team members on front-end design, development, and performance.

## **NEFTA Solutions - Software Engineer**

2004 - 2006

Contributed to developing Servlets and JSP page to redesign applications and in analyzing and fixing production bugs.

### Areas of Excellence

Experience architecting large-scale multi-tier web applications, Experienced with MEAN and MERN Stack, Agile Development, GIT Workflow, Creative Problem Solving & Analytical Skills, Quick Learner, Commitment, Motivator, and Mentor.

## **EDUCATION**

#### KAKATIYA UNIVERSITY, INDIA - Master of Computer Applications

#### **Professional Development & Awards**

Received Client Appreciation from American Express in Q1 – 2010, 2011, 2014, 2019 Certified Scrum Master (CSM) & Product Owner Certified Flash MX Developer